<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A mirror; wherein the rumpers and fanaticks (especially those, who even yet desire to continue religious rebells, and to make piety the sire to treason, and new disturbances;) may see their deformity, and abhor both themselves and their actions. Sent in a letter by a friend, to a votary and follower of that faction. Occasioned by a seditious sermon lately preached.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1660</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 28 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 8 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A89171</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing M2225</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E1034_14</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R209041</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99867949</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99867949</idno>
            <idno type="VID">168925</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A89171)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 168925)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 153:E1034[14])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A mirror; wherein the rumpers and fanaticks (especially those, who even yet desire to continue religious rebells, and to make piety the sire to treason, and new disturbances;) may see their deformity, and abhor both themselves and their actions. Sent in a letter by a friend, to a votary and follower of that faction. Occasioned by a seditious sermon lately preached.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 13, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed for Robert Pawley at the Rainbow in Fleetstreet,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1660.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "July 24".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Religion and politics --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Commonwealth and Protectorate, 1649-1660 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:168925:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A Mirror; Wherein the RUMPERS AND FANATICKS (Eſpecially thoſe, who even yet deſire to continue <hi>Religious Rebells,</hi> and to make Piety the Sire to Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, and new Diſturbances;) may ſee their defor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity, and abhor both themſelves and their Actions.</p>
            <p>Sent in a Letter by a Friend, to a Votary and Follower of that FACTION.</p>
            <p>Occaſioned by a Seditious Sermon lately Preached.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Pſal. 59.12.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>For the ſin of their mouth, and the words of their lips, let them even be taken in their pride; and for Curſing and Lying which they ſpeak.</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Hor: lib. 3. Ode 4.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <l>Vis conſilii expers mole ruit ſuâ.</l>
               <l>Vim temperatam Dii quoque provehunt,</l>
               <l>In majus; iidem odere vires</l>
               <l>Omne nefas animo moventes.</l>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Robert Pawley</hi> at the <hi>Rainbow</hi> in <hi>Fleetſtreet,</hi> 1660.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:168925:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:168925:2"/>
            <head>A Mirror, &amp;c.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I Suppoſe you will readily grant, that if a Perſon hath a <hi>limb</hi> or a <hi>member</hi> cut off, there needs not many Arguments to perſwade him, that there is a <hi>maym</hi> and a <hi>deformity</hi> in his Body: And ſurely I think it is equally <hi>ſenſible,</hi> and will therefore require as little labour to prove, that in this lat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Age of the World there never was more viſible tokens of a Divine diſpleaſure upon any Nation, than this of <hi>England,</hi> which being <hi>poſſeſſed</hi> with many <hi>legions</hi> of <hi>Evil ſpirits,</hi> moſt <hi>fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious</hi> and <hi>fanatick,</hi> hath, from their <hi>Impulſes,</hi> for many years to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, been like a great body <hi>tearing</hi> it ſelf to pieces. During a tedious interval of time we lay gaſping under the groans and preſſures of a <hi>Civil Uſurpation:</hi> from thence (like our Saviour, delivered from the <hi>Tyranny</hi> and <hi>Injuſtice</hi> of <hi>Pilate,</hi> to the <hi>rudeneſs</hi> and <hi>violence</hi> of his <hi>Souldiers</hi>) we were tranſmitted to a <hi>Military Inſolence:</hi> When thoſe Perſons, who, before they had <hi>built</hi> their fortunes upon <hi>publick ruines,</hi> we ſhould have diſdained to have ſet with the dogs of our Flock, were become our <hi>Dictators,</hi> and the <hi>grand Maſters</hi> of our <hi>Lives,</hi> our <hi>Properties,</hi> and our <hi>Laws;</hi> all which lay like a <hi>Partridge</hi> under a <hi>Falcons</hi> wing, ready to be ſeizd upon, and torn in pieces at their pleaſure. Wee have known committed the moſt irregular and exorbitant Tyrannies, aggra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vated from one part of the Actors from a <hi>mercinary perfidiouſneſs,</hi> and more highly aggravated from the other party by a <hi>pretended legality,</hi> which endeavoured to make the Vaſſallage certain, and irrevocable. <hi>Religion, Juſtice, Counſil,</hi> and <hi>Treaſure,</hi> thoſe four Pillars of Government were undermined, and in part demoli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed: We were indeed a meer <hi>heap</hi> and <hi>rout</hi> of Men hudled to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:168925:3"/>like the Emblem of Diſorder. And now, that from all this Miſery and Confuſion we are in ſome meaſure emancipated. When thoſe <hi>Daemoniacks,</hi> which, (like him in the Goſpel) hath many times thrown the Nation into the <hi>fire</hi> of War and Rapine, and many times into the <hi>Water</hi> of Violence and Deſolation, are almoſt <hi>charm'd</hi> and <hi>exorcis'd;</hi> And when a moſt <hi>diſtemper'd</hi> People, whom we may properly ſay, <hi>Satan</hi> hath <hi>bound</hi> theſe <hi>eighteen years,</hi> are in ſome aſſurance of being <hi>looſed</hi> from their <hi>infirmity:</hi> When the dawnings of a happy Settlement break forth upon us, and when, (to endear the Mercy,) all this is ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſhed without blood and ſweat, in ſuch an unexpected and ſudden change of Providence, that no <hi>Oracle</hi> could have found belief, if any had foretold it: That yet notwithſtanding any Perſon ſhould be ſo beſotted with <hi>Ignorance,</hi> or ſo <hi>everwhelm'd</hi> with <hi>Malice,</hi> and <hi>Self-intereſt,</hi> as ſtill to dote upon our Enſlavers, and conſequently, to deſire a Return of our Madneſſe and Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traction, is even the moſt prodigious Wonder; which as in my ſelf it produceth <hi>pity</hi> and <hi>amazement,</hi> ſo in others it cannot but beget both <hi>ſcorn</hi> and <hi>indignation.</hi> For how can it be thought upon, otherwiſe than with a reflection of horror, that becauſe ſome <hi>corrupt ſtomacks</hi> are able to digeſt <hi>poyſon,</hi> all others muſt be forbidden the uſe of more wholeſom dyet? It is true, there was a time when theſe State-Conjurers, did with ſo many <hi>clouds</hi> wherein their Actions were inwrapt, fill the paſſages of Mens underſtanding, that the beam of the mind could not ſet open the light of Reaſon; but now that thoſe thick Scales are faln off, and all that <hi>painting</hi> and <hi>varniſh</hi> with which their pretences were adorn'd, is now diſſipated and vaniſhed, for men ſtill to continue their deſires to uphold ſo corrupt an Intereſt, doth not admit either Excuſe or Pardon, ſeeing it doth not proceed from <hi>Ignorance,</hi> or <hi>Error,</hi> but from a <hi>perverſe ebſtinacy,</hi> and a <hi>Malici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Ambition.</hi> It is a true ſaying of one of the Antients, that <hi>Time</hi> and the <hi>Eye</hi> try out <hi>truth,</hi> but <hi>falſhood</hi> winneth eredit only
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:168925:3"/>on a <hi>ſudden,</hi> and by <hi>uncertainties:</hi> And ſince Time, the moſt ſure and impartial Judge, hath ſentenced thoſe glorious preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, with which our late Politicians did veyl themſelves, to be nothing elſe by <hi>gilded Hypocriſies,</hi> and the baiting of their hook with Heaven to catch Earth; he that ſubſcribes not to this Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimony, muſt even defie the light it ſelf. Naturaliſts tell us of the Baſilisk, that if he ſee a Man firſt, the Man dies, but if a Man ſee him firſt, the Baſilisk dies; It is moſt certain of thoſe politick <hi>frauds</hi> and <hi>impoſtures,</hi> uſed by thoſe exquiſite <hi>State-Jugglers</hi> late<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly turn'd out of <hi>Play;</hi> Many Perſons, not being quick-ſignted enough to diſcern them, they did not only <hi>endanger,</hi> but <hi>deſtroy;</hi> but now they are <hi>diſcovered,</hi> all their power of doing hurt is loſt, except over thoſe, who chuſe to prefer Rebellion with <hi>ruin,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Subjection with <hi>Safety.</hi> I think it may be a queſtion con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning many of our grand Tyrannizers, whether their <hi>Perſons</hi> were more contemptible, or their Actions more to be deteſted? For there was obtruded upon the Nation, not only <hi>vaſſallage,</hi> but <hi>contumely:</hi> How many of them grew, like <hi>Melons,</hi> out of Dunghils? Whom that Character which <hi>Tacitus</hi> gives of ſome <hi>Promooters</hi> in his time may aptly expreſſe, Of <hi>Beggars</hi> they are become <hi>Rich,</hi> Of <hi>Contemptible</hi> perſons <hi>feared,</hi> procuring deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction to others, and in the end to themſelves. Should their Actions be deſcribed, the <hi>Illegality, Injuſtice, Rapine,</hi> and <hi>Vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence</hi> which was interwoven and coexiſtent with them, would fill a <hi>Volume</hi> as big as the <hi>Book of Martyrs;</hi> And, were they not moſt eminently notorious, and impoſſible to be hidden, I ſhould ſay as <hi>Seneca</hi> in the like Caſe, <hi>Satius erat ista in oblivionem ire, ne quis poſtea Potens diſceret, invideretque rei minimè humanae.</hi> How<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever, my intentions are not to <hi>ſtain</hi> my Paper with the things themſelves, but only to note their <hi>Circumſtances,</hi> and <hi>atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dants.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I am perſwaded, ſince man-kind had a being, there was never joyned together <hi>fairer</hi> reſemblances, and <hi>ſouler</hi> Ends, then in
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:168925:4"/>thoſe men. How well may that be applyed to them, which <hi>Herodian</hi> obſerves of the Emperor <hi>Severus,</hi> that he was the moſt cunning <hi>Diſſembler</hi> in the World; not regarding to falfify his Oath to ſerve his <hi>Ambition;</hi> one that knew how to <hi>inſinuate</hi> into others, for his own purpoſes, And would readily utter that with his <hi>tongue,</hi> which he never intended in his <hi>heart.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Never was that precept of <hi>Lyſander</hi> ſo well practiſed, as by theſe <hi>Statiſts,</hi> That Children are to be deceiv'd with <hi>Comfits,</hi> and men with <hi>Oathes.</hi> Never was there <hi>beast</hi> who had more foul and ſtinking <hi>garbage</hi> cover'd over with a fair skin. Never was there <hi>Crocodile</hi> who was more <hi>plentiful</hi> in tears, nor more ready to <hi>devour:</hi> They were like the <hi>Cane-plant,</hi> which of all Plants, as it is <hi>Smootheſt</hi> in bark, ſo it is <hi>holloweſt</hi> in body.</p>
            <p>But that which gave the moſt horrid aſpect, and the moſt noyſome favour to all their impieties, (like a taper in the hand of a Ghoſt, or as ſweet Oyle to a rank and ſtinking body,) was, that <hi>Religion</hi> was forced to become a <hi>Fander</hi> to their Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranny and Ambition: And as the Heathens of old, fancied <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piter</hi> to be an <hi>Adulterer, Mars</hi> a <hi>Quarreller, Bacchus</hi> a <hi>Drunkard, Mercury</hi> a <hi>Thief,</hi> and <hi>Venus</hi> a <hi>Whore,</hi> that having ſuch Patrons for their Vices, their <hi>uncleanneſs</hi> might ſeem <hi>Religious;</hi> So theſe Politicks would needs fancy <hi>God</hi> to be ſuch a one, as themſelves, by <hi>intereſting</hi> him in all their <hi>deſigns;</hi> and after the Plot was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triv'd, he was implor'd to give the Succeſſe, though the thing it ſelf was never ſo <hi>Villanous;</hi> and if the Iſſue was ſutable to their deſires, then they boaſted that they were <hi>delivered</hi> to doe ſuch abominations. <hi>Caſuiſts</hi> ſay, He that <hi>lyes</hi> with his Siſter commits a heinous Crime, but he that <hi>marryes</hi> his Siſter heigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tens his impiety, by applying <hi>Gods Ordinance</hi> to his own Villa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny: Surely there cannot be a more profligate and flagitious Act, then to make God the <hi>Patron</hi> of <hi>fraud,</hi> and to uſe <hi>Religion</hi> as a Mask to cover their <hi>lewd deſigns.</hi> And indeed, how can thoſe impious wretches be ſufficiently abhorred, who being full
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:168925:4"/>fraught with Malice, and Ambition, lift up <hi>polluted hands</hi> to heaven; And are neither afraid nor aſhamed to approach the moſt holy of Religious duties, being yet polluted with the blood of their <hi>Murders</hi> and <hi>Regicides?</hi> Theſe are the Perſon, who whilſt their Actions gave the cleereſt evidences of <hi>Cruelty</hi> and <hi>Sacrilege, Diſloyalty</hi> and <hi>Perfidiouſneſs,</hi> did notwithſtanding not ceaſe to be devout. But what was the Efficacy of their Devoti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on? Surely nothing more than the correcting of their <hi>geſtures,</hi> and the reforming of their <hi>hair;</hi> it did not in any meaſure re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe their <hi>paſsions,</hi> nor touch their <hi>Vices,</hi> nor reſtrain and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent their <hi>Treaſon</hi> and <hi>Tyranny.</hi> Their greateſt vertue conſiſted in extolling thoſe <hi>offendors,</hi> whom their own Examples and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands having made like the <hi>Evil Angels,</hi> they nevertheleſſe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted to be <hi>Saints,</hi> and in ſpeaking evil of thoſe <hi>Innocent Perſons,</hi> whom having injured with the greateſt <hi>oppreſsion,</hi> they alſo bran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded with the moſt <hi>infamous</hi> terms. Their <hi>Zeal,</hi> which according to the phraſe of the Holy Ghoſt, ought to have <hi>eaten up them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves,</hi> did devour their <hi>Neighbour,</hi> and made a Conflagration, not only of Towns and Provinces, but of Kingdoms and Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. What did they gain by their frequency of Converſe with holy things, more than the <hi>contempt</hi> which growes from <hi>familia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity,</hi> and the Cuſtom to violate, and porfane them? They be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came more confident to commit Wickedneſſe, and willingly loſt the <hi>ſcruple,</hi> that with the left cheek they might <hi>purſue</hi> the ſin. So that we may believe they made uſe of Religious Exerciſes, not ſo much to implore pardon for their enormities, as liberty to perpetrate more, and to ſin with authority. Theſe àre they, who did certainly fancy that all Villany was permitted them, provided they did but retein a <hi>ſhew</hi> of Piety. Theſe were they, who mingled God among their <hi>Paſsions,</hi> though never ſo <hi>irre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular</hi> and <hi>exorbitant;</hi> that ingaged <hi>him</hi> in their <hi>Intereſts,</hi> though never ſo miſchievous and <hi>corrupt;</hi> and employed <hi>him</hi> upon all oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſions where <hi>Avarice, Rapine, Murders,</hi> and <hi>Uſurpations</hi> were to
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:168925:5"/>be promoted. And, that which is not leaſt to be admired, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding their <hi>pretended</hi> Sanctity, was at length even mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt to all, to be but a <hi>vizard</hi> of ſpecious Hypocrifie, yet ſtill they continued to make uſe of it, thereby to abuſe the People: Being, as I conceive, ambitious to <hi>exalt</hi> their <hi>Impudence,</hi> to the ſame degree with their <hi>Impiety,</hi> I could wiſh that there was no ſuch cauſe to affirm of theſe Men, that as they took the ſureſt courſe to <hi>make</hi> other Perſons Atheiſts, ſo their own handling of holy and religious things, diſcovered themſelves to be worſe than Atheiſts. It was one principal part of their aym, to multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply diviſions in Religion, that ſo, a <hi>Spiritual Anarchy,</hi> might be engaged to ſupport their <hi>Civil Uſurpation;</hi> Now it is obſerved of old, That many diviſions in Religion are a principal cauſe to introduce Atheiſm. Doubtleſſe ſuch <hi>Schiſms</hi> are a greater <hi>Scandal,</hi> than <hi>corruption</hi> of Manners: For what can be the effect of ſuch a <hi>Morris-dance</hi> of Sectaries) each of them having a di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers <hi>Poſture</hi> and <hi>Cringe</hi> by themſelves) but to move deriſion and Contempt in Worldlings and depraved Men, who are too prone to ſcorn and reject piety and holineſſe. But on the other ſide, If any <hi>Atheiſt</hi> did but reflect upon thoſe Nefandous and Atroci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Crimes, which thoſe corrupt Polititians have committed, under a pretence to advance the Cauſe of Religion, He would ſurely be a thouſand times more Atheiſt than before, and with ſcorn and deteſtation cry out,
<q>Tantum Religio potuit ſuadere malorum.</q>
            </p>
            <p>It muſt needs be more commendable to have <hi>no Opinion</hi> of God at all, than to entertain ſuch thoughts as are not only <hi>unwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy</hi> of him, but <hi>Contumelious</hi> and <hi>Reproachfull</hi> unto him: It is ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved, that the <hi>Devils Blaſphemie</hi> was, <hi>I will Aſcend, and be like the moſt High.</hi> But <hi>thoſe mens Blaſphemie</hi> exceeds that of <hi>Lucifers,</hi> for they make the moſt High <hi>Deſcend,</hi> and become like the <hi>Prince</hi> of <hi>Darkneſs.</hi> For what elſe can it be, to <hi>Intereſt God</hi> in thoſe exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crable
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:168925:5"/>Actions of <hi>Murthering Princes, Butchering</hi> People, and the <hi>Ruin</hi> and <hi>Subverſion</hi> of States and Governments?</p>
            <p>And what now is the effect of all, but this only, That having filled their Sailes with the <hi>Breath</hi> of Religion, <hi>Profit</hi> was the Compaſſe, by which thoſe Land-Pirates ſteerd their Courſe in all our miſchievous Commotions: For the reſt, it is moſt evident to any who have but the leaſt portion of underſtanding, that they have deſtroyed the moſt Glorious and Excellent Common-wealth, which the world could boaſt off; A Common-wealth which was beſt Ballanced, and moſt equally Tempered between <hi>Royal Prerogative,</hi> and the <hi>Peoples Liberty,</hi> each Suppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting and Maintaining the other: Nor is it poſſible, for any form of Government upon Earth, more really to ſecure the peoples Rights, than that: Nor to give unto them, either a more aſſured Redreſſe of <hi>Material Grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vances,</hi> or a clearer exemption from all Burdens, and Tax<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ations, but ſuch as themſelves ſhall concur in the Impoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. And yet our late State-<hi>Mountebanks,</hi> were like that famous Quackſalver <hi>Paracelſus,</hi> who counting it a trivial <hi>over-worn</hi> way, to maintain the world as <hi>God</hi> himſelf had provided, thought fit to propoſe a mean for the Propagation of Mankind without the uſe of <hi>Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men.</hi> Or, as it is Fabled of <hi>Ixion,</hi> that projecting with himſelf to enjoy <hi>Juno</hi> the <hi>Goddeſſe</hi> of <hi>Power,</hi> he had Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulation with a <hi>Cloud,</hi> of which he begot <hi>Centaures,</hi> and <hi>Chimaeras,</hi> ſo theſe men being carried away with a <hi>Frantick</hi> and <hi>Impotent</hi> Paſſion, and a <hi>Vapourous</hi> conceit of forming ſome <hi>Imaginary</hi> model of Government, which they did eſpecially defign to have <hi>Perpetuated</hi> in themſelves, are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed <hi>delivered</hi> of nothing but <hi>ayrie hopes,</hi> and certain moſt <hi>deformed,</hi> and <hi>monſtrous Apparitions.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="8" facs="tcp:168925:6"/>
            <p>But Sir, to paſſe from theſe unto your ſelf; Is it not moſt ſtrange, that as <hi>Glaveus</hi> praiſed <hi>Injuſtice,</hi> and <hi>Iſocrates</hi> extolled <hi>Buſiris</hi> that notable Tyrant, ſo theſe mens <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendations</hi> ſhould be your Subject, or their <hi>Restauration</hi> your Deſire? And is it not equally wonderful, that ſuch Lectures ſhould be heard with any Approbation and Allowance? But I perceive it is upon the ſame Reaſon, that <hi>Tacitus</hi> gives of the Applauſe afforded to <hi>Aliniue Gallus</hi> for his defence of <hi>Luxury</hi> and <hi>Prodigality,</hi> The ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledging of <hi>Vices</hi> under <hi>honeſt terms,</hi> and the <hi>likeneſſe</hi> of <hi>Affections</hi> in your hearers minds, cauſeth their aſſent to be eaſie and favourable: Nor can the ſtrength of your Arguments be any other, than ſuch as <hi>Anthony</hi> the <hi>Orator</hi> was once forc'd to uſe; who, being to defend a Perſon, that was accuſed of Sedition and Treaſon, bent all the force of his Eloquence to prove, that <hi>Sedition</hi> and <hi>Treaſon</hi> were no Crimes. Surely it will do well if you take pains to conſider, That ſuch an Enterprize as you endeavour, Is as <hi>Vain,</hi> as it is <hi>Impious:</hi> There never wanted any thing to the overthrow of thoſe <hi>Stateſ-men,</hi> which you ſo magnifie, but only to have the people <hi>undeceiv'd</hi> and reſtor'd to their <hi>Right wits:</hi> For that which was long ſince objected to, and anſwered by that Excellent <hi>Phocion,</hi> (with whom expired the Liberty of his Country, which procur'd his Ruine) may both waies here be moſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly applied; One told him, that if ever the People grew <hi>Enraged,</hi> they would kill him; <hi>Phocion</hi> anſwered, Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>adventure they may kill me when they are <hi>Mad,</hi> but if ever they grow <hi>Sober</hi> again, they will not ſuffer thee to live. They who have advantag'd themſelves by the <hi>Frenzie</hi> of the Vulgar, they will aſſuredly <hi>Abominate,</hi> if now they are return'd unto their ſober temper. So
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:168925:6"/>that your old Patrons have two potent Enemies to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counter withall, that is to ſay, <hi>Heaven,</hi> and <hi>Earth; Heaven</hi> for their <hi>Blaſphemie,</hi> and <hi>Earth</hi> for their <hi>Deceit;</hi> You therefore who are ſtill their followers, do but la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour to kindle a <hi>Fire,</hi> by blowing of <hi>dead Aſhes,</hi> which if you continue to endeavour, you will but too clearly manifeſt a ſtrange Compoſition of <hi>Folly,</hi> and <hi>Fury</hi> to be in you, and you muſt give others leave to take it, not as an evidence of your <hi>Saintſhip,</hi> but as an Argument of your <hi>Stultitude.</hi> And certainly as the <hi>Enterprize</hi> is Ridiculous, ſo the <hi>Impiety</hi> is Incompara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble; For what can be more unbecomming him, whoſe Office is to be an <hi>Ambaſsador</hi> of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> than to demean himſelf as an <hi>Herald</hi> to <hi>Belzebub?</hi> Or to bring down the <hi>Holy Spirit</hi> not in the likeneſſe of a <hi>Dove,</hi> but in the form of a <hi>Vultur,</hi> or a <hi>Raven?</hi> It was an Excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent ſaying of <hi>King Henry the 7th.</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> That <hi>when Chriſt came into the world, Peace was Proclaimed, and when he left the world, Peace was bequeath'd.</hi> How then can they pretend to be his Miniſters, who in their Conſcionatory Invectives, <hi>breath</hi> nothing but <hi>Blood, Ruine</hi> and <hi>Confuſion?</hi> And rather ſay as <hi>Jehu</hi> did, <hi>What haſt thou to do with Peace? Get thee behind me:</hi> As if Peace were not their buſineſſe, but <hi>following,</hi> and Parties, and Factions. I cannot but believe that a Miniſter inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medling in Court and State affaires, deſerves as ſevere Scourges, as a Marchant who buyes and ſells in the Temple. However they ought to be ſuch ſtudious Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers of Concord and Amity, that they ſhould even avoid a <hi>Seditious Truth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I know what you pretend to fear, and what you are bold to affirm, That <hi>Popery</hi> will be introduc'd, and that
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:168925:7"/>the <hi>King</hi> is already a <hi>Papiſt;</hi> for the firſt, let me tell you, (although this old <hi>Jeſuitick</hi> Juggle doth not deſerve an Anſwer) that it is an Objection only of your <hi>Suſpition,</hi> not your <hi>Reaſon:</hi> And yet it is ſuch a Suſpition, that as it imports the greateſt ſcandal to the State, ſo it implies a moſt Sottiſh contradiction in it ſelf: For all men know, That they who firſt rays'd a Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit to themſelves, by faſtening that <hi>Imputation</hi> upon others, did in the exerciſe of that power, which partly by that <hi>aſperſion</hi> they obtained, give a perfection to thoſe deſignes, which the Pope and his Partiſans, although they often deſired to effect, was never able to accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſh; And it is now fully evinced, That the <hi>Beaſt with ſeven heads,</hi> and the <hi>Beaſt with many heads,</hi> have both the ſame deſigne, to make Princes as the <hi>Banditi,</hi> and at their own pleaſure to <hi>proſcribe</hi> their Lives, their Revenews, and their Kingdoms: So that it cannot but be the ſtrongeſt ſymptom of a Fanatique Fancy, to imagine, that the ſame Perſons ſhould bee inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mental to return us to that madneſſe and confuſion, from which they have even now freed us, and are ſtill labouring to protect, both themſelves and the Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</p>
            <p>As to the other part, the truth is, you follow the rule of depraved Nature, though it be moſt unſutable to Chriſtianity, You <hi>hate</hi> him whom you have <hi>wronged:</hi> And as it is ſaid of the Dragon, that when he cannot <hi>reach</hi> his prey, he <hi>poyſons</hi> the Air with his <hi>breath,</hi> and ſo deſtroyes it; So becauſe you cannot <hi>touch</hi> his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſties Body, you labour to <hi>blaſt</hi> his <hi>Peputation;</hi> And now that your Company of <hi>Lying Wonders</hi> for the <hi>Publick good,</hi> fail, and are become uſeleſſe, you have
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:168925:7"/>recourſe to <hi>lying Slanders,</hi> and perhaps intend to make your Libels, and defamatory Speeches, to be Succeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors to the Popes Legend. Surely theſe <hi>Politick con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tumelies</hi> are a recent Invention of this corrupt age; or old they us'd them not: For it might as well have been objected againſt <hi>David,</hi> that he was a Worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per of <hi>Dagon,</hi> when <hi>Saul</hi>'s furie and injuſtice forced him to fly to King <hi>Achiſh,</hi> and the Philiſtines. But of this thus much only need be ſaid, <hi>Tenne eſt menda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cium pellui et ſi diligenter inſpexeris.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By this time, Sir, I hope you ſee that four-fold miſchiefe in which you are implicated, Your <hi>Deſires</hi> are Impoſſible, your <hi>Attempts</hi> are wicked, your <hi>Fears</hi> are vain, and your <hi>Reports</hi> are falſe and ſcanda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous: And is it poſſible that after all this, any Perſon ſhould be ſuch a ſuperlative Fanatick, as to need ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trinſick argumen's to reclaim him? Surely it cannot bee; except he bee rooted in his Errour, as they ſay <hi>Marſus Diaboli</hi> rootes in ſelf in the Earth, which can never be pulled up without breaking. However I doe not doubt, but, as <hi>Suetonius</hi> reports, that <hi>Auguſtus Cae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſar</hi> walking by a Pond where the Froggs were croak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, commanded them to keep ſilence, and they were never after heard to make any Noyſe in that Place: So all that harſh roaring, and diſcordant clamour both in pulpits and other places, which hath not only <hi>por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended,</hi> but <hi>caus'd</hi> ſo much miſchief in the Kingdom, (like the Prognoſtications of ſome Conjurers, that <hi>fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tell</hi> the tempeſts they intend to raiſe) will ere long by the preſence and command of our <hi>Auguſtus</hi> be ſilenc'd and reſtreyn'd.</p>
            <pb n="12" facs="tcp:168925:8"/>
            <p>I have now done: Only ſuffer me to adde this, What I have writ, although it be <hi>bitter,</hi> yet it is <hi>whole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome:</hi> There can not be a perfect Converſion, unleſs a full Conviction do proceed: Eſpecially in a caſe of this nature it is indiſpenſably neceſſary; For thoſe perſons, who have hitherto triumphed over our lawes, and would now triumph over our ſenſes, as well as our reaſon and judgement, by perſwading us that <hi>Tyranny</hi> is <hi>liberty: U<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurpation, juſtice:</hi> and <hi>Preſſures</hi> and <hi>burdens, Eaſe</hi> and <hi>Reſt,</hi> will not be reclaimed, until they perceive that their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>praved and corrupt Principles, and their crooked and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe Rules, are as deeply ſounded, and as plainly diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covered to others, as they are known unto them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves.</p>
            <p>I know that the wound given to the State wants <hi>Oyle,</hi> rather then <hi>Vinegar</hi> to be pour'd into it. But he is no good Phyſitian, that doth not in ſome caſes, as well accomodate his Receipts to the <hi>temper</hi> of the Patient, as to the <hi>nature</hi> of the Diſeaſe. Some wounds are not fit for an <hi>healing</hi> plaiſter, except a <hi>Corroſive</hi> be firſt apply<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. And in this diſtemper you your ſelf have prov'd it neceſſary; And that is the reaſon I am forced to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve that Method of Phyſick, which cures one <hi>heat</hi> by <hi>another.</hi> I ſhall conclude with this cordial deſire, That as the King is called Gods Vicegerent, So that he may make him the pattern, and examplar of his Proceeding, by ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending a plentifull pardon to <hi>penitent offenders,</hi> ſo far as his <hi>mercy</hi> may not violate his <hi>justice:</hi> but they who will ſtill continue <hi>perverſe</hi> and <hi>Contumacious,</hi> let them <hi>periſh</hi> in their <hi>Obſtinacy.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="13" facs="tcp:168925:8"/>
            <q>
               <lg>
                  <l>Rarò antecedentem ſceleſtum</l>
                  <l>Deſeruit pede poena claudo.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Seldom the Villain, though great haſte he make,</l>
                  <l>Slow-footed Vengeance fails to overtake.</l>
               </lg>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Prov: 24.24, 25</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>He that ſaith unto the wicked thou art Righteous, him ſhall the people curſe, Nations ſhall abhor him. But to them that rebuke him ſhall be delight, and a good bleſsing ſhall come upon them.</p>
            </q>
            <trailer>THE END.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
